<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../sdocbook.dtd">
<section>
	<title>Trentino Introduction</title>
	<para>
TRENTINO is an open source platform that enables and simplifies the task of developing and managing SOA based embedded systems by providing a comprehensive infrastructure based on Service Component Architecture (SCA) standard.
Trentino severely reduces complexity and thus has positive implications on cost during the entire application lifecycle of your product.
	</para>
	<section>
		<title>Enable extensible architectures</title>
		<para>
			Trentino has been designed from the ground up to eliminate complexity
			at both architecture and API levels.
			It provides the following keys features to the embedded developers
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para> A standard based component model
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Plugable communication protocols (SCA Bindings)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>A Management and monitoring component for Trentino
						applications
					</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Distributed Service discovery
					</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Trentino is non invasive: Minimal API, use of dependency
						injection. It therefore facilitate the migration of existing C++
						code base to a Trentino Runtime.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Lightweight Runtime</title>
		<para>
			The main goal of Trentino is to be as lightweight as possible. An empty
			Trentino runtime has a memory footprint lower than 500 KB.

		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Target users</title>
		<para>
			Trentino has been designed as generic as possible to be integrated in allmost
			all kind of embedded applications. The minimal requirements for
			Trentino is that
			the embedded device should host an Operating System. The Source code can
			be compiled for Visual Studio and GCC platforms (including QNX).

		</para>
		<para>
			Trentino is licensed under Apache License, Version 2.0. Full commercial
			support is available from Siemens Corporate Technology.
			Tooling for Trentino applications are provided.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Contribution development process
		</title>
		<para>The development of an SCA contribution (see glossary for definitions) is done in four steps:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para> Develop and test SCA services
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para> Assemble SCA contribution
					</para>
				</listitem>				
				<listitem>
					<para>Prepare for deployment using Trengen
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Deploy on a Trentino runtime
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>

<para></para>
</section>